Orsini Family Papers, ca. 1150-1950 (bulk 1500-1900)
UCLA Library Special Collections
Orsini Family Papers
ca. 1150-1950 (bulk 1500-1900)
902
Orsini family.
560 boxes (280 linear ft.) 12 oversize boxes. 132 images of maps, plans, and other documents
The Orsini are one of most important families in Italian history. At the height of their influence, in the late Middle Ages and into the Renaissance, the Orsini were crucial players in Italian politics; they were closely allied to the Medici, with whom they were tied by several high-level marriages. The family produced three popes, about thirty cardinals and 62 senators of Rome, as well as several electors of Saxony and Brandenburg, and grand masters of the Knights of Malta. They were related to a number of royal houses of Europe. The papers consist mainly of material relating to the administration of property (including records of sales, leases, mortgages, loans, proxies, accounting, inventories and plans) and the administration of the family (including dowries and marriage contracts, donations, divisions of property, wills and fideicommissums). There is also a substantial amount of legal material, mostly produced by the many law-suits in which the family was involved, and correspondence, largely dating from the 18th century. Access to selected digital images of plans, maps and other materials in the Orsini Family papers is available on the UCLA Digital Library webpage.
Gli Orsini sono una delle famiglie più importanti della storia italiana. All'apice della loro influenza, nel tardo Medioevo e nel Rinascimento, gli Orsini furono attori cruciali nella politica italiana; erano stretti alleati dei Medici, a cui erano legati da vari matrimoni ad alto livello. La famiglia generò tre papi, circa trenta cardinali, sessantadue senatori di Roma nonchè vari elettori di Sassonia e Brandemburgo e gran maestri dell'Ordine dei Cavalieri di Malta. La famiglia aveva legami di parentela con varie case reali d'Europa. Le carte consistono in gran parte di materiale relativo all'amministrazione di proprietà (vendite di proprieta, affitti, mutui, prestiti, procure, contabilità, inventari e piante, ecc.), e all'amministrazione della famiglia (doti, contratti di matrimonio, divisioni e donazioni, testamenti e fidecommessi, ecc.). Vi è anche una quantità sostanziale di materiale legale, prodotto principalmente dalle molte cause nelle quali la famiglia fu coinvolta, e corrispondenza, soprattutto del settecento. È possibile accedere ad una selezione di immagini digitali delle piante, mappe ed altro materiale delle carte Orsini al sito della UCLA Digital Library.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Department of Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Zeitlin & Ver Brugge, purchase, 1965.
Collections are processed to a variety of levels depending on the work necessary to make them usable, their perceived user interest and research value, availability of staff and resources, and competing priorities. Library Special Collections provides a standard level of preservation and access for all collections and, when time and resources permit, conducts more intensive processing. These materials have been arranged and described according to national and local standards and best practices.
We are committed to providing ethical, inclusive, and anti-racist description of the materials we steward, and to remediating existing description of our materials that contains language that may be offensive or cause harm. We invite you to submit feedback about how our collections are described, and how they could be described more accurately, by filling out the form located on our website: Report Potentially Offensive Description in Library Special Collections.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9924704363606533
Biography/History
The Orsini are one of most important families in Italian history. At the height of their influence, in the late Middle Ages and into the Renaissance, the Orsini were crucial players in Italian politics; they were closely allied to the Medici, with whom they were tied by several high-level marriages. The family produced three popes, about thirty cardinals and 62 senators of Rome, as well as several electors of Saxony and Brandenburg, and grand masters of the Knights of Malta. They were related to a number of royal houses of Europe. The papers consist mainly of material relating to the administration of property (including records of sales, leases, mortgages, loans, proxies, accounting, inventories and plans) and the administration of the family (including dowries and marriage contracts, donations, divisions of property, wills and fideicommissums). There is also a substantial amout of legal material, mostly produced by the many law-suits in which the family was involved, and correspondence, largely dating from the 18th century.
***
Gli Orsini sono una delle famiglie più importanti della storia italiana. All'apice della loro influenza, nel tardo Medioevo e nel Rinascimento, gli Orsini furono attori cruciali nella politica italiana; erano stretti alleati dei Medici, a cui erano legati da vari matrimoni ad alto livello. La famiglia generò tre papi, circa trenta cardinali, sessantadue senatori di Roma nonchè vari elettori di Sassonia e Brandemburgo e gran maestri dell'Ordine dei Cavalieri di Malta. La famiglia aveva legami di parentela con varie case reali d'Europa. Le carte consistono in gran parte di materiale relativo all'amministrazione di proprietà (vendite di proprieta, affitti, mutui, prestiti, procure, contabilità, inventari e piante, ecc.), e all'amministrazione della famiglia (doti, contratti di matrimonio, divisioni e donazioni, testamenti e fidecommessi, ecc.). Vi è anche una quantità sostanziale di materiale legale, prodotto principalmente dalle molte cause nelle quali la famiglia fu coinvolta, e corrispondenza, soprattutto del settecento.
Expanded Biographical Narrative
The Orsini
The Orsini rose to power in Rome in the late 12th and 13th centuries, as a few families filled the gap created by the struggle between a weakened papacy and a fledgling communal government. During that time the family acquired scores of feudal lands in the Papal States and the Kingdom of Naples. In Rome their urban fortresses at Monte Giordano and Campo de' Fiori dominated the surrounding area, acting as strongholds in the battles which periodically broke out between Orsini supporters and the supporters of their enemies and rivals for supremacy in Rome, the Colonna. Over the following centuries, the Orsini's private armies and enormous wealth made them crucial players in the complicated power game of Italian politics. The family remained preeminent in Italian political and religious life into the 19th century, eventually producing three popes, about thirty cardinals and 62 senators of Rome, as well as several electors of Saxony and Brandenburg, and grand masters of the Knights of Malta. They were related to the royal houses of France, Spain, England, Denmark, Sweden, Norway and Poland.
The Orsini of Bracciano
The Orsini of Bracciano descended from a line which remained relatively undistinguished until the early 15th century, when the sons of Giovanni Orsini (d. post 1398) made a name for themselves as condottieri. They skillfully built on the wealth and power acquired through their condotte. Francesco (d. 1456) eventually earned the title of Prefect of Rome and acquired the Duchy of Gravina, beginning the line of that name (see below). Carlo (d. post 1445) and his sons continued the line of Bracciano; they consolidated their hold over this key seigneurie, and reinforced and expanded a constellation of properties of great strategic importance in the countryside north of Rome. Carlo's grandson Gentile Virgino (d. 1497) was also key player in this enterprise, aided in part by his close alliance with Lorenzo de' Medici (1449- 1492). The tie between the two families, established through the marriage of Lorenzo to Clarice Orsini di Monterotondo (d. 1488), was renewed in the following generation with the union of Piero de' Medici (1471-1503) and Alfonsina Orsini (1472-1520), and in 1553 with the marriage of Paolo Giordano Orsini (1541-1585) to Isabella de' Medici (1542-1576).
The 16th century, in addition to this and other important alliances, saw the elevation of Bracciano to a Duchy. It also, however, marked the beginning of the Orsini's gradual decline, as a series of ambitious non-Roman popes challenged the power of the Roman barons. The family's position was further weakened in this period by financial difficulties, and shaken by a series of murders within the family. The 17th century too was marked by renewed honors and advantageous marriages, including that of Paolo Giordano II (1591-1646) to Isabella Appiani, ruler of Piombino. Still, neither these, nor a rich inheritance from the Orsini of S. Gemini, nor the elevation of two members of this line cardinalate, helped to rescue the family from its vertiginous financial decline. At the end of the century Flavio Orsini Duke of Bracciano (1620-1989), the last member of the line, was obliged to sell his titular fief and other property. He left his remaining patrimony to his second wife, Anne Marie de la Tremoille, sparking a decades-long legal challenge from the Orsini of Gravina, the closest line in the family. Their attempt to reclaim the Flavio's ancestral properties was ultimately unsuccessful. Among the properties inherited by Anne Marie was the archive of the Orsini of Bracciano.
The Orsini of Gravina
The Orsini of Gravina, whose line continues today, descended from Francesco Orsini, Prefect of Rome (d. 1456). His base shifted away from Rome when he acquired the County of Gravina, in southern Italy, through his marriage in 1418 to the wealthy heiress Margherita della Marra. Francesco's descendents expanded their holdings in southern Italy, partly thanks to their close ties with the Aragonese rulers of Naples. In the 16th and 17th centuries a series of marriages with important families such as the Caracciolo, Sanseverino and Frangipani della Tolfa reinforced the Orsini's power base in the Kingdom of Naples, and added to their network of properties. They gravitated towards Naples, where they built a distinguished Renaissance palazzo (Palazzo di Gravina). In 1724, about a quarter century after the extinction of the line of Bracciano, Pietro Francesco Orsini was elected to the papacy, taking the name of Benedict XIII (1649-1730). Though not a financial boon, his election gave the family renewed prestige and a heightened role on the Italian stage. It was also due to this pope that the archive of the Orsini of Bracciano was recovered from the descendents of Anne Marie de la Tremoille, and combined with that of the Gravina line.
Benedict XIII's grandson Domenico Orsini (1719-1789) was the continuator of the line, but was created Cardinal in 1743, after the death of his second wife. In addition to his long ecclesiastical career, Domenico continued to act as head of the family, administering properties and supervising an extensive restoration of the Naples palace at the hands of the architect Mario Gioffredo, with contributions from Luigi Vanvitelli and Ferdinando Fuga. The 19th century was marked by financial difficulties and endless legal battles with creditors. By the end of the century the south Italian properties had been lost to creditors, and within decades the Roman palace, and the archive were also sold. The first part of the archive was sold in 1904 to the Archivio Storico Capitolino. The second part was put on the market in 1963, and eventually bought by Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
***
Gli Orsini
Gli Orsini ascesero al potere a Roma nel tardo dodicesimo e nel tredicesimo secolo, in un momento in cui il vuoto di potere creato dalla lotta fra un papato indebolito e un giovane governo comunale veniva riempito da alcune importanti famiglie locali. Durante questo periodo gli Orsini acquisirono quantità vaste di terre nello Stato Pontificio e nel Regno di Napoli. A Roma le loro fortezze urbane a Monte Giordano e Campo dei Fiori dominavano le aree circostanti, funzionando da piazzeforti nelle battaglie che scoppiavano periodicamente fra i sostenitori degli Orsini e quelli dei Colonna, loro nemici e rivali per la supremazia a Roma. Durante i secoli seguenti gli eserciti privati degli Orsini e le loro immense ricchezze fecero di loro attori cruciali nel complicato gioco di potere della politica italiana. La famiglia rimase preminente nella vita politica e religiosa fino al diciannovesimo secolo, generando tre papi, trenta cardinali, sessantadue senatori di Roma nonchè vari elettori di Sassonia e Brandemburgo e gran maestri dell'Ordine dei Cavalieri di Malta. La famiglia aveva inoltre legami di parentela con le case reali di Francia, Spagna, Inghilterra, Danimarca, Svezia, Norvegia e Polonia.
Gli Orsini di Bracciano
Gli Orsini di Bracciano discendevano da una linea che rimase relativamente oscura fino all'inizio del quindicesimo secolo, quando i figli di Giovanni Orsini (d. post 1398) si fecero un nome come condottieri. Essi costruirono abilmente sulle ricchezze e il potere acquisiti con le loro condotte. Francesco (d. 1456) ebbe il titolo di Prefetto di Roma e acquisì il Ducato di Gravina, dando inizio al ramo della famiglia legato a questo nome. Carlo (d. post 1445) e i suoi figli continuarono la linea di Bracciano. Essi consolidarono il loro controllo di questa signoria chiave, e rinforzarono ed ingrandirono una costellazione di proprietà di grande importanza strategica nel territorio a nord di Roma. Il nipote di Carlo, Gentile Virginio (d. 1497), fu un attore importante in questa impresa, aiutato in parte dalla sua alleanza con Lorenzo de' Medici (1449-1492). Il legame fra le due famiglie, instaurato con il matrimonio di Lorenzo con Clarice Orsini di Monterotondo (d. 1488), fu rinnovato nella generazione successiva con l'unione di Piero de' Medici (1471-1503) con Alfonsina Orsini (1472-1520) e nel 1553 con il matrimonio di Paolo Giordano Orsini (1541-1585) con Isabella de' Medici (1542-1576).
Il sedicesimo secolo, oltre a queste ed altre importanti alleanze, vide l'innalzamento di Bracciano a Ducato. Al tempo stesso marcò l'inizio del graduale declino degli Orsini, dato che una serie di ambiziosi papi non romani cominciarono ad erodere sistematicamente il potere dei baroni romani. La posizione della famiglia fu ulteriormente indebolita in questo periodo da difficoltà finanziarie, e scossa da una serie di uccisioni all'interno della famiglia. Anche il diciassettesimo secolo fu marcato da nuove onorificienze e matrimoni vantaggiosi, incluso quello di Paolo Giordano II (1591-1646) con Isabella Appiani Signora di Piombino. Ciononostante, né questi matrimoni, né la ricca eredità degli Orsini di San Gemini, né l'innalzamento di due membri di questa linea alla porpora cardinalizia, aiutarono la famiglia ad arrestare il vertiginoso declino finanziario. Alla fine del secolo Flavio Orsini, Duca di Bracciano (1620-1689), l'ultimo membro di questo ramo, fu costretto a vendere il ducato di Bracciano e molte altre proprietà. Lasciò i resto del suo patrimonio alla seconda moglie Anne Marie de la Tremoille, dando inizio ad una decennale disputa legale intentata dagli Orsini di Gravina, il ramo più vicino della famiglia. Il tentativo di questi ultimi di reclamare le proprietà avite di Flavio finalmente fallì. Fra le proprietà ereditate da Anne Marie c'era l'archivio degli Orsini di Bracciano.
Gli Orsini di Gravina
Gli Orsini di Gravina, il cui casato continua ancora oggi, discendevano da Francesco Orsini Prefetto di Roma (d. 1456). La base di Francesco si spostò da Roma quando egli acquisì la Contea di Gravina nel sud dell'Italia, attraverso il suo matrimonio nel 1418 con la ricca ereditiera Margherita della Marra. I discendenti di Francesco ingrandirono i loro possedimenti nel sud dell'Italia, in parte grazie ai loro stretti legami con gli Aragonesi signori di Napoli. Nel sedicesimo e diciassettesimo secolo una serie di matrimoni con importanti famiglie come i Caracciolo, i Sanseverino, e i Frangipane della Tolfa rinforzarono la base di potere degli Orsini nel Regno di Napoli, e aumentarono le loro proprietà. Essi gravitavano intorno a Napoli, dove costruirono un importante palazzo rinascimentale (Palazzo Gravina). Nel 1724, circa un quarto di secolo dopo la scomparsa del ramo di Bracciano, Pietro Francesco Orsini venne eletto papa, prendendo il nome di Benedetto XIII (1649-1730). Questa elezione, nonostante non rappresentasse un importante incremento finanziario, diede alla famiglia un rinnovato prestigio e ne rinforzò il ruolo sulla scena italiana. Fu anche grazie a questo papa che l'archivio degli Orsini di Bracciano fu recuperato da un discendente di Anne Marie de la Tremoille, e ricongiunto con quello del ramo di Gravina.
Il nipote di Benedetto XIII, Domenico Orsini (1719-1789), era il continuatore del casato, ma fu eletto cardinale nel 1743 dopo la morte della sua seconda moglie. Durante la sua lunga carriera ecclesiastica Domenico continuò ad agire come capo della famiglia, amministrando proprietà e dirigendo un importante restauro del palazzo di Gravina, affidato all'architetto Mario Gioffredo con contributi di Luigi Vanvitelli e Ferdinando Fuga. Il diciannovesimo secolo fu marcato da difficoltà finanziare ed interminabili battaglie legali con i creditori. Entro qualche decennio erano stati venduti il palazzo di Roma e l'archivo. La prima parte dell'archivio fu venduta nel 1904 all'Archivio Storico Capitolino. La seconda fu messa sul mercato nel 1963, e in seguito comprata da Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Scope and Content
Most of the documents in the Orsini Family Papers at UCLA come from the combined archives of the lines of Bracciano and Gravina, but they also touch on other lines, such as those of Monterotondo, Mugnano (Bomarzo) and Sangemini. They include three major categories of documents: administrative papers, legal material and correspondence.
The administrative material includes records of property sales, leases, mortgages, loans, accounting, inventories and plans. Most of it concerns the Orsini but also related or allied families, as well as subjects and litigants. Aspects of the administration of the family itself are also covered, including dowries, marriage agreements, divisions and transfers of property, wills and fideicommissums.
The legal material is the product of the many the law-suits in which the family was involved. Most of these concerned property and inheritance rights, but there are also records of trials of Orsini subjects.
A significant proportion of the collection is made up of 18th-19th century correspondence, mainly that of Card. Domenico Orsini (1719-1789), as well as of several of his descendants. Other aspects of the family's life documented by the papers include their honorific titles, relations with the papal state, interactions with foreign courts, and documentation on the churches and monasteries with which the Orsini were connected.
Other aspects of the family's life documented by the papers include their honorific titles, including the important one of "Assistente al Soglio Pontificio," interactions with foreign courts, and documentation on the churches and monasteries with which the family was connected. There are several boxes of material connected to the administrative reforms of Pope Pius IX (1876-1874) in the Papal States during the Italian Risorgimento.
Access to selected digital images of plans, maps and other materials in the Orsini Family papers is available on the UCLA Digital Library webpage.
***
La maggior parte delle carte della famiglia Orsini all'UCLA provengono dagli archivi combinati dei rami di Bracciano e Gravina, ma interessano anche altri rami come quelli di Monterotondo, Mugnano (Bomarzo) e Sangemini. Essi includono tre categorie di documenti: carte amministrative, materiale legale e corrispondenza.
Il materiale amministrativo include vendite di proprieta, affitti, mutui, prestiti, procure, contabilità, inventari e piante. La maggior parte di questi documenti concerne gli Orsini ma anche famiglie imparentate o alleate ad essi, e anche sudditi e parti avverse. Sono coperti anche aspetti dell'amministrazione della famiglia stessa, con doti, contratti di matrimonio, divisioni e donazioni, testamenti e fidecommessi.
Il materiale legale è il prodotto delle molte cause nelle quali la famiglia era coinvolta. Molte di queste concernono diritti di proprietà e di eredità. C'è anche materiale relativo a processi che riguardano i sudditi degli Orsini.
Una parte significativa della collezione è costituita dalla corrispondenza del diciottesimo e diciannovesimo secolo, principalmente quella del cardinale Domenico Orsini (1719-1789) con i suoi amministratori e agenti nelle proprietà degli Orsini. C'è anche corrispondenza amministrativa di vari discendenti di Domenico.
Altri aspetti della vita della famiglia documentati dalle carte includono i loro titoli onorifici, compreso quello importante di Assistente al Soglio Pontificio, rapporti con corti straniere, e documentazione sulle chiese e monasteri ai quali la famiglia era legata. Ci sono varie scatole di materiale relativo alle riforme amministrative dil papa Pio IX (1876-1874) nello Stato Pontificio durante il Risorgimento.
È possibile accedere ad una selezione di immagini digitali delle piante, mappe ed altro materiale delle carte Orsini al sito della UCLA Digital Library.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Geneaologie (Partial Genealogies)
Titoli (Bulls, Briefs and Letters Patent)
Città, Stati, Feudi e Castelli (Instruments and Other Papers Regarding the Administration of Properties, both Urban and Rural)
Piante di Feudi e Proprietà (Plans of Lands, Houses, Palaces and Castles)
Inventari (Inventories of Urban and Rural Properties)
Stati Esteri (Documents on the Orsini's Relations with Foreign Courts)
Alimenti (Instruments and Other Papers Concerning Alimonies)
Bolle (Copies of Bulls and Other Declarations)
Censi (Instruments Concerning the Creation of "Censi" [Loans Linked to Real-Estate])
Concordie (Instruments of "Concordia" [Agreements or Settlements of Disputes])
Dichiarazioni (Various Legal Declarations)
Divisioni di Beni (Instruments of Division of Property)
Donazioni (Instruments of Donation)
Doti e Capitoli Matrimoniali (Instruments Establishing Dowries and Marriage Agreements)
Obbligazioni (Instruments Declaring Indebtedness)
Procure (Proxies)
Quietanze (Instruments of Receipt)
Suppliche (Various Petitions)
Testamenti (Testaments)
Varie Commerciali (Instruments Concerning Commercial Transactions)
Varie Legali (Instruments Concerning Legal Transactions)
Vendite (Instruments of Sale)
Assistenza al Soglio Pontificio (Documents on this Privilege [Assistant at the Papal Seat])
Enti Ecclesiastici (Documents Concerning Various Ecclesiastical Entities)
Propaganda Fide (Documents on the Congregation of the Propaganda Fide)
Stato Pontificio (Risorgimento) - (Documents Concerning the Administrative Reforms Made in the Papal States by Pius IX)
Cause (Lawsuits)
Eredità (Papers Concerning Inheritance)
Fedecommessi (Papers Concerning the Orsini Properties Subjected to "Fedeicommissum")
Contabilità Amministrativa (Account Books Concerning the Income and Expenses of the House of Orsini)
Contabilità Domestica (Account Books Concerning the Domestic Expenditures of the Orsini of Gravina)
Contabilità Monte Orsini (Papers Concerning the Financial Entity Called Monte Orsini)